<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://flyingburri.to/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://flyingburri.to/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-03T17:11:15+00:00</updated><id>https://flyingburri.to/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Flying Burrito</title><subtitle>The personal blog of Julian Vergel de Dios AKA Flying Burrito. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Papa - Lesson 2</title><link href="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2025/lessons-from-papa-lesson-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Papa - Lesson 2"/><published>2025-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://flyingburri.to/blog/2025/lessons-from-papa-lesson-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2025/lessons-from-papa-lesson-2/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is part of a series memorializing my dad, Rolando Vergel de Dios, who passed away unexpectedly on November 29th, 2024. For the full context it’s best to start at the beginning: <a href="/blog/2024/lessons-from-papa-lesson-1">Lesson 1</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-cigarette-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-cigarette-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-cigarette-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-cigarette.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Black and white photo of Papa posing with a cigarette in front of a wall for his entry in the Asian Institute of Management yearbook c. 1978" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-motorcycle-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-motorcycle-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-motorcycle-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-motorcycle.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Black and white photo of Papa posing next to his motorcycle at a building at the Asian Institute of Management c. 1978" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Papa looking cool for his yearbook photos at the Asian Institute of Management c. 1978 </div> <hr/> <p>My uncles, my cousins, and several of Papa’s friends all described him as effortlessly cool. Whether it was stories of him dancing the night away at the famous club that was the epicenter of Manila’s 70s disco culture known as Cocobanana. Or donning a helmet and carving his way through the snarled gridlock of Manila’s roadways on his Honda Scrambler motorcycle. Or his Tom Selleck of Manila mustache. They all idolized him for his ability to exude this maverick persona.</p> <p>Part of that devil-may-care air-of-cool was always having a cigarette in hand. From what I remember by the early 90s, about the time he was going to turn 40, he had been a pack-a-day guy for almost 20 years. The 90s is also when big tobacco was finally coming clean about what cigarettes could do to you and how much damage they could do to not just you, but the people around you inhaling your secondhand smoke.</p> <p>By this time, I had also already started showing signs of childhood asthma. It was clear to Papa that the cigarettes had to go. But, knowing that kicking the habit would be a high-effort endeavor, he figured out that he could use the occasion to extract a little more value out of his son. He decided he would make me a deal: you get straight As on your next report card and I’ll quit smoking. A heavy burden to put on a 1st grader.</p> <p>It was the beginning of the school year and it would be six weeks before my next report card. I desperately wanted Papa to be healthier and I knew that the cigarettes weren’t good for my breathing either, so I worked diligently for that 6 weeks and got my straight As. The day after I presented him with my report card he quit cold turkey.</p> <p>His methods may have been questionable, but I can’t argue that they weren’t effective.</p> <p>The lesson I learned from Papa that day: people will run through brick walls for you if you figure out what motivates them.</p>]]></content><author><name>flyingburrito</name></author><category term="papa"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is part of a series memorializing my dad, Rolando Vergel de Dios, who passed away unexpectedly on November 29th, 2024. For the full context it’s best to start at the beginning: Lesson 1.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up Jekyll and al-folio</title><link href="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/setting-up-jekyll-and-al-folio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up Jekyll and al-folio"/><published>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/setting-up-jekyll-and-al-folio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/setting-up-jekyll-and-al-folio/"><![CDATA[<p>When I decided to set up my blog I had a few requirements:</p> <ul> <li>Manage content entirely via git</li> <li>Static pages only (no backend rendering pages dynamically)</li> <li>Deploy to Github Pages or equivalent</li> <li>RSS feed compatibility</li> <li>SEO best practices implemented automatically</li> <li>Accessibility best practices implemented automatically</li> </ul> <p>I’m a Rubyist at heart, so <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a> seemed to be the most logical choice. It checks a lot of the boxes above by default, with others being supported by plugins. I followed the quickstart and in short order had a basic Jekyll dev instance set up with the default Minima theme.</p> <p>While an excellently flexible tool, the base install leaves a lot to be desired. Minima isn’t <em>bad</em> but it left a lot of things for me to do myself and I wanted a little bit more of a full package included. I started searching for themes that would fulfill what I wanted while being minimalist and content focused. That’s when I found <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a>. It definitely benefitted from the phonebook effect of showing up first in an alphabetical list, but it had pretty much the rest of the list that I wanted and a few other bonuses. Weird quirk: it’s designed for academics to share their CV, projects, and publications, which I don’t currently need, but could come in handy in the future I guess.</p> <p>I did run into a few issues getting the Github Actions to run without errors as well as having to dig into issues and other places to get some customizations that I wanted, so I’m documenting what I found here to hopefully save other people time.</p> <h1 id="github-actions-errors">Github Actions errors</h1> <p>I kept getting broken link errors when building my pages which didn’t prevent the site from deploying but were annoyingly sending failure emails with every push. Interestingly the main things causing errors were actually the default documentation markdown files for al-folio. After I deleted <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">README.md</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INSTALL.md</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CONTRIBUTING.md</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CUSTOMIZE.md</code> those errors all went away.</p> <h1 id="hiding-pages">Hiding Pages</h1> <p>I didn’t need most of the pages that were included in the default al-folio installation, but didn’t exactly know how to remove them without literally deleting them from the template (which I didn’t want to do if I needed to bring them back). The answer was in this Github question: https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions/2031</p> <p>In the frontmatter for any of the pages there is an optional <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nav</code> variable that you can set to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">false</code> if you want to omit it from the nav bar. Here is my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cv.md</code> file’s frontmatter:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nn">---</span>
<span class="na">layout</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">cv</span>
<span class="na">permalink</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">/cv/</span>
<span class="na">title</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">cv</span>
<span class="na">nav</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="kc">false</span> <span class="c1"># &lt;---- this is what you want to change</span>
<span class="na">nav_order</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">5</span>
<span class="nn">---</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h1 id="post-metadata">Post Metadata</h1> <p>There were a few pieces of metadata that aren’t directly documented that I had to figure out:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">author</code>: I assumed this would be inferred from the name in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code> but it has to be explicitly set per post</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">og_image</code>: I assumed that this could be automatically pulled from the first image in the post body, but this also needs to be explicitly set</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>flyingburrito</name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="tech"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I decided to set up my blog I had a few requirements:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Papa - Lesson 1</title><link href="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/lessons-from-papa-lesson-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Papa - Lesson 1"/><published>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/lessons-from-papa-lesson-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://flyingburri.to/blog/2024/lessons-from-papa-lesson-1/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been thinking of starting my blog for years at this point, but I never thought something like this would be the final push or the topic of my first post.</p> <p>My father, Rolando “Roly” Vergel de Dios, passed away suddenly and unexpectedly on November 29th, 2024. Many of his friends and family know him as Rolando, Roly, or <a href="https://jonsquared.wordpress.com/2008/04/23/filipino-sibling-hierarchy/">Diko</a>, but my brother Gabriel and I know him as Papa. To say this has upended my life and the lives of everyone in my family would be an understatement. It’s been 3 weeks and I still have the disorienting feeling that none of this is real and that I will wake from the nightmare soon. Sadly that day isn’t coming, so I’m left to try and make sense of something that will never make sense to me. That my father is gone and that I’ll never again be able to speak with him or ask him for advice. I’ll never again be able to call him to share my good news or my sorrows. It’s cliché but I truly didn’t understand how large a loss this would be until it happened, despite spending a good deal of time worrying about it for both of my parents.</p> <p>I decided to search his name on Google after he passed and was kind of sad to find that there really isn’t much of a digital footprint for him out there. The only thing is <a href="https://www.holycrossmortuary.com/obituary/rolando-vergel-de-dios">the generic obituary page</a> that the mortuary created for us automatically with nothing other than his photo and dates of birth and death. In my life and in my family he is a larger than life presence. A booming voice, thunderous laughter, and always the life of the party wherever he goes. Part of this exercise is me grieving, but I also feel strongly that such a presence should have a place here, some marker of his existence.</p> <p>As a Filipino family, we did the traditional 9 night novena prayer for him over Zoom, with family and friends signing in from all over the world. Each night a different group of people offered a eulogy with memories of times that they shared with him. It was amazing to hear how many lives he’d touched. I was the last to do mine on night 9, and I’m sharing an expanded version of that here. This will be a series of posts that offer up a different lesson that I learned from him depicted as little vignettes from my life growing up as his son.</p> <p>I love you, Papa. I miss you, and I will every day for the rest of my life.</p> <p>Hold your loved ones close, you really never know when they’re going to go.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-julian-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-julian-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-julian-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/lessons-from-papa/papa-julian.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Me and Papa at the South Bay Galleria c. 1988. I'm less than 2 years old and Papa is embracing me close in his arms." loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Me and Papa at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Bay_Galleria">South Bay Galleria</a> c. 1988 </div> <hr/> <p>I grew up in a suburb of Los Angeles in the 90s. I still live in the same neighborhood to this day. It’s basically the ideal of post-WW2 United States. Cute minimal traditional style homes with manicured lawns on comfortably large lots with big back yards. They once upon a time housed factory workers for the booming LA aerospace industry.</p> <p>I took full advantage of the big back yard. One glorious Christmas morning I awoke to a very large wrapped present in that very yard. After tearing it open what I found was a PowerWheels Army Jeep. If you don’t know what that is, it’s a child-sized, plastic, battery-powered, motorized replica of a WW2 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willys_MB">Willys Jeep</a>. It was slow but man was it badass. I would imagine missions to clear mines out from behind the garage, slowly making my way into enemy territory. If Gabriel and I were getting along I would let him ride shotgun, or if I was really in a generous mood he would get to drive it. I loved that thing.</p> <p>I went to a preschool nearby the house, close enough to walk or bike, although given that this is Los Angeles my parents still drove to pick me up and drop me off. Papa was who was usually charged with that duty.</p> <p>I’ll never forget this one time at the end of the school day. Just as we were about to let out, something unusual was brewing outside. Papa and my French grandfather, Papy (who was visiting from across the Atlantic), had hatched a delightfully mischievous plan. They’d quietly maneuvered the Jeep into position on the sidewalk next to the gate alongside the regular line of minivans and sedans in the pickup lane.</p> <p>As I shuffled out with my classmates, tummy rumbling for an afternoon snack, I spotted them first – two grown men wearing matching conspiratorial grins, standing proudly beside the tan and camo colored Jeep. My heart leapt. Whatever was happening, I knew it would be good.</p> <p>I waved goodbye hurriedly to my friends, already breaking into a run. Their confused expressions turned to pure amazement as I scrambled behind the wheel. With Papa’s encouraging nod and Papy’s twinkling eyes watching, I slammed my foot on the accelerator. The look on my classmates’ faces was priceless – a mix of disbelief and envy as I, a mere preschooler, drove myself home that day. I felt like the star of my own movie, rolling away from school in perhaps the most spectacular exit of my young life.</p> <p>The lesson I learned from Papa that day: you can find fun in even the most mundane everyday activities.</p>]]></content><author><name>flyingburrito</name></author><category term="papa"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been thinking of starting my blog for years at this point, but I never thought something like this would be the final push or the topic of my first post.]]></summary></entry></feed>